Software engineering radio episode 43
extreme programming part two.
Hi everybody. Um, this is Alex and Arno
again speaking about um, extreme
programming. Actually, this is the
second part um, of the episodes about
extreme programming.
And this episode is taking a more
overall process related and business and
context and organization related look at
extreme programming. Um, the first
episode
explained the more technical hands-on
side of things.
And this time we're we'll start by
looking at the practices of extreme
programming.
But we're now going to look at those
practices that are more related to the
overall process, to the context in which
extreme programming is. And then we'll
look at the context of a project doing
XP.
How to get the buy-in, how to get it
started, how
what rhythm it has, how deliverables are
done, what sort of contracts you can do.
So, extreme programming in the context.
So, shall we dig in?
Yeah. And I guess we should start with
the user stories, which are great.
What are user stories? It's not like
that time stories, is it?
Maybe sometimes.
Um, user stories are the
the heartbeat of an XP project.
Actually, they are the requirements, but
they are more than this.
Um, in XP you don't do um, a lot of
extensive um, requirement work. You
don't do you a lot of use case diagrams
and all this that stuff. Um,
what you do is actually you you you ask
your customer to give you the story of
the feature he wants to have. That's why
it's called a user story. So, it is kind
of a use case centric approach. It's
it's feature driven.
Um, and the story is actually it behaves
or feels like a story um, for your
customer.
And this story um,
is written down on an index card and um,
it's just a one or two sentence thing.
You you don't do all the
deep and and and fancy requirement stuff
you can
or requirement collecting stuff you can
do there. Um, it's more like a promise
for communication. That's how it's
called in in some XP literature.
So, story might be a little misleading
here. Actually, you just take an index
card and write one or two sentences that
explain at the abstraction layer of the
customer some feature
um, or something that should be in the
um, in the system you're building.
Exactly. So, something like calculate
rates for whatever. Um, it's it's just a
simple sentence long enough to to um,
that the customer is able to remember
what he wanted once he has written this
and everybody can can um, remember what
what it means or uh, imagine what it
means but not enough to code actually
the the things down. So, you need your
customer afterwards um, to to ask what
he wants and do all the the test stuff
and all that.
engineering means you have some people
on site customers or proxies of the on
site customer or whatever way you want
to implement it and they were sort of
turning in index cards writing sort of
memos for that only they really
understand that
give uh, markers for them to explain
more in more detail later and then they
put them in a cardboard box and this
cardboard box is sort of the
requirements document.
Exactly. And
the these cards
will be taken out by developers
afterwards. We will touch this when we
we do the discuss the planning game and
can be brought to your your desktop
when you use the task. So they are more
than just a requirement document
actually. They are an artifact to to
yeah, to the heartbeat of the project as
called. So you use it as a
as a token to to drive your project
actually.
So yeah, we'll go into more detail when
we're looking at the planning game. But
just to to give a short idea to put this
in context.
Um
the developers or the these cards are
prioritized by the customer for the
iterations and then the developers ask
for details on the most highly
prioritized cards and then they estimate
them and then there's a negotiation
which goes into this first into this
iteration and only one iteration is
planned in advance basically.
Mhm.
Exactly.
And afterwards the the cards are getting
thrown away.
on the wall to show how much work got
done or whatever.
Okay, but we'll go into more detail of
later. Um this but you said it was
heartbeat. I was taught the um
this the iterations were the heartbeat
which actually is the next practice.
Yeah. Um
depends on your your
picture of heartbeat.
Actually we
the iteration are the the the the the
metric the the the beat of
the timely beat yes for for the process
stuff.
But the stories are the driving factor.
Without stories your team gets
no more things to do. So actually that
once happened to me in a project I
worked in XP project
where we had a
well not an onsite customer but our
customer was the the guy who who was in
the on-site customer role actually uh
hadn't have the time to do new stories,
to do get new input in our our project
actually run dry. So, it's it's the the
pushing uh factor in in XP.
Yeah. That's why I Yeah, yeah. I was I
was just joking cuz um it's not obvious.
It will become obvious when we go into
the planning game why it is the
heartbeat. Yeah.
Yeah.
So, uh it you you you touched
iterations. Um
next primary practice are the little
weekly cycle, so-called,
um which are the iterations.
Where you do all the stuff you usually
do in a in a
huge project. Um you you do the
planning, you do implementation, uh
testing, release. So, the the whole
iteration cycle usually fits into one or
um
two weeks. Uh depends a bit on taste how
long it is.
But, it's called weekly cycle.
but the idea is to actually have
deliverable software at the end of the
week. So, it's not just hypothetical,
but you actually burn a CD or whatever
and give it to whoever is interested in
it to receive feedback. Yeah. So, this
is actually releases. It's not just
hypothetical um labels on the
versioning system. It really is an
integrated, tested release that is
given out.
It's a complete project, if you want. A
a complete cycle
that you do. Complete release, yes,
every week.
How much overhead does this sort of um
release involve? I mean, in I I've been
in projects where the the overhead of
getting a release done was several weeks
all by itself. So,
how much how much overhead does that
involve?
That
actually could be a problem. Um
not so much because of the overhead on
the the team side, because usually when
you do an XP project, you do everything
you can do releases in a simple way. So,
Uh, everything in in an XP project is is
uh focused to make things automated. You
have your unit test, so you don't need
an a long better or whatever testing
phase before you can release it. So,
everything in XP does it or tries to to
make these simple releases or
not so costly releases.
Um, but the problem often, or at least
in my past, was that the customer isn't
able to handle this.
Even if you do two weekly releases, not
so many customers have the time to do
tests on two weekly releases. So, um,
actually I had some problems in in in
the past.
Yeah, but well, I think even if the
customer doesn't isn't able to handle
this release, it's still valuable
because it helps to focus
and keeps to to stay close to having a
releasable software. It helps to, um,
yeah, to to think about small steps that
um, lead to incremental value
and to divide the work into little
things that do not break anything big.
Absolutely correct, but it's
in my
or it was it's tougher to to get a team
to do a real release every week if no
one cares for it. So,
um, there there was some problem for me.
And yes, you're right, it's not just for
getting feedback from the customer, it's
it's important to a lot of
integration work as early as possible
because otherwise you get a huge heap
you have to do sometime at the end of
the project. So, doing releases every
week is good for the project alone, even
if feedback isn't a necessary point
here. But it's it's tough to get a team
to do it regularly
or so often,
when no one really cares for it. So,
yeah.
One one
more word of caution here. In my
experience, this release does not have
to meet all the usual criteria for
release.
Um, usually if you actually do release,
um, there are, let's say, data migration
requirements.
And which are which take effort that
usually is not necessary for every
single of these weekly releases. They're
just sort of to give the customer a
hands-on feeling. And also you In my
experience, um, these are not as
thoroughly tested as actually final
releases needs to be. They are just to
show the customer the direction the
project is going in.
So, if it is less stable or not as well
integrated with other systems as
is desirable and needs to be done in the
end, that is okay for this sort of
releases. Just to keep the overhead low
and enable rapid feedback.
Mhm.
Okay.
Um
Besides these weekly cycles, there are
also the quarterly cycles, which are not
so much iteration cycles, but you have
to do the, well, call it higher-level
management stuff. You have to to
plan your real releases for for
customers or if you have a product and
not a project, you you have to do
marketing stuff and plan all this time
stuff. You have to plan resources,
people, timetables,
all this stuff. And that's done in a
somewhat quarterly,
yeah, cycle.
Sort of to get this sort of thing done
that needs to be done long in advance.
You
In the everyday work, you don't want to
bother with thinking ahead and planning
long in long ahead, which is part of the
XP philosophy, way of doing things, but
sometimes you need to do that. So, once
every quarter or
at whatever frequency, you sit down,
take the time to really think ahead, and
sort of try to guess the future.
But still it's important to to mention
here that the detail level is different
from what other
development processes do in this
quarterly cycle. So, you don't do
detailed timetable planning what some
guy does in 3 months or on a daily
basis. That's not the idea. The idea is
get the big picture actually, and
afterwards you you have to correct your
your maybe false
plannings anyway. So, it it's really the
the the high-level stuff and it's
necessary to to keep a company
flowing.
So, I guess that well, the the big
Yes, this is cycle stuff, the the time
time stuff.
We we have some other primary practices
to discuss
that are not so well related or I don't
see a common topic. Uh first one is
slack,
um which is um well, the idea is simple.
Just plan slack um because you need it.
You you need to clean up your code. You
need to
place around. Uh you need to do
research. You need to to learn stuff.
So, you you have to plan in slack
somewhere. Um
I'm not sure how this was handled in the
first edition of XP, but I I I guess
there was no slack actually in
It actually
I think we we remember
went into this in the first episode when
we discussed pair programming. And
actually, that is where it is in the
first episode because pair programming
tends to keep you busy all the time and
tends to conflict tends to
well, tends to put peer pressure on you
even if it No one really expects you to
focus all the time. You sort of want to
impress others by not being the first
one to say, "I need some time off." So,
um this is closely related to pair
programming, I think. And you you need
really need to create a culture where
it's okay to say, "I need to uh some
time to do my emails. I need some time
to do research." Whatever. So, actually
to allot whatever number of hours to
encourage people to actually take this
slack.
Yeah. But, it's actually
also for the higher level stuff, not
only the the 10-minute breaks and while
pair programming
the the the second edition of the book
actually says you you have to plan for
time out and stuff like that. So,
it's also on a higher level.
So, someone might say,
"I need to do research. Give me I'll be
back next week."
Give me a month. Yeah, exactly.
yeah. I mean, this sort of thing
actually happens without XP. And in XP,
you really need to make it explicit to
encourage people.
Yeah, exactly.
So, next
practice?
Yeah, this is really one of my
favorites.
Yeah, mine too. I have a lot of trouble
with that right now.
Okay, what what's the idea?
You have to set a marker how long you
build might take and every time you you
you go beyond this time limit,
do something to get
below again. So, the the idea is
and this time level is mostly
well, there there's no real rule how to
find it or where it has to be. But, the
But, the rule of thumb that I like to
use is
developers need to feel comfortable with
it.
The build people should not feel that
the build gets in the way of getting
things done.
Yeah, exactly.
And 10 minutes is is a good
well, good idea where
where a limit is where a team gets into
trouble.
Yeah, actually I I I would place the
limit a lot lower. Somewhere from 2 to 5
minutes is my rule of thumb.
But anyway, yeah.
This obviously varies from team to team.
Yeah. And one problem here is of course
or what of course, that's
very dependent on the technology you
use.
That is one of the things
you can
well, at least you can do
when you use stuff like Smalltalk or
Java or C# or whatever. Um, my project
right now is a huge C++ project and it's
very hard to do it below 12 minutes.
Right, yeah. This This is but this is
sort of a problem of C++.
Yeah, exactly. So,
you see some of the techniques are
actually even technology dependent in XP
and and come from the background where
the guys
worked before. They They did Smalltalk,
they did Java. Um,
of course they did C++ projects too, but
but their main focus is these
techniques. So, you might get into
trouble with some of the techniques in
different environments.
but let's take a look at what this
10-minute build really is about. I mean,
the idea is that every developer is able
to perform a complete automated build
on her
own workstation
regularly in order to execute the tests
and executing the tests is part of this
build. So, the important thing is that
people don't just use their IDE to um,
sort of
um, oh, there's a bug over there, but
I'll just ignore it. It's very popular
with people who use Eclipse. Um,
but actually everybody is able to do in
real build the to execute the build
script that actually goes into the
production build as well.
And execute this build script which
compiles everything and um, also
executes all the tests on a regular
basis. This is sort of an enabling
technique for um,
for rapid integration for um
especially for test-driven development.
But, what can I do if I can't do it as
simply? I mean, um
as I said, C++ takes some time to
compile, and computers are as fast as
they are now. And if my build right now
takes 4 hours, okay, maybe I can
optimize it to take 2 hours, but 10
minutes are is
Well,
but there are techniques for C++ that um
speed up your build. For example,
um decouple the system into several
compilation units,
and then um decouple the builds,
and check in the results of the
compilation into the version control
system,
so that you only need to recompile the
um
um the compilation unit you actually
you've actually made changes to and link
it to the checked-in compilation units
of the other
um
uh the other compilation units.
Okay, so so so your answer is actually
do whatever you can to to get to a to a
short
build integration.
Exactly, yes.
Because I mean, there is a lot of
effort, and some I know projects where
even the link link uh run
takes longer. So,
nevertheless, you say do everything you
can
I would Yes, I would say that, and I
mean, otherwise, you probably extreme
programming is not the process for you,
I would say.
But especially, keep down the time as as
far as you can,
because otherwise, test-driven
development will not be done.
Because you need to
build the system in order to run your
tests.
And if building the system takes 2
hours, you just will not run your tests
after every single change.
But we're getting to the to the next um
practice actually, I think, which is
continuous integration.
Exactly.
Well, I I think
a lot of what we said for the 10 minute
build
yeah well fits good to the continuous
integration topic.
The idea is of course to to integrate as
soon as often even continuous
as possible because the the cost of
integration grows over time
exponentially. So
the idea is to to do it as soon as
possible get feedback as soon as
possible
that's why
that's why we talked
so much about the 10 minute build.
To do this your build needs to be fast
because anytime you want to check in
the idea is to to get an integration
build as soon as you check in.
Yeah this this is the
sort of the ideal.
There are tools different languages for
example cruise control for Java that
does just this.
It's coupled to the version control
system and every time someone commits a
change an automatic build is started and
if it fails mails go out. This is sort
of the the high high ideal.
Yeah exactly.
And if you you take a look at the higher
level
the basic idea is the same with the
weekly cycle. I mean even the weekly
cycle with the weekly release is some
kind of the idea to integrate as soon as
possible to get feedback as soon as
possible. Same idea here.
And
taking your comment going back to your
comment about C++
I have numbers from the 90s
that even the people at Microsoft
working on Windows NT
did a complete build every night.
And so obviously this probably took more
hardware than just a single workstation.
But even there they did this continuous
integration as continuously as was
possible which was every night and they
ran what they called smoke tests
in some some little test suite that
showed if at least the rudimentary
functionality worked. So, this is
possible even for huge projects done in
statically linked languages.
Yeah. As far as I know that they kept
the the
they did the same thing. It just wasn't
10 minutes.
They they set a time limit and they kept
their build under this time limit for a
very very long time. Don't know if it's
still true, but
it it worked for them for a long long
time.
Yeah.
Well, I think this is one of the
practices that gets discarded quite
frequently actually because when because
it's so simple to sort of just ignore it
this. Oh, the break the build broke.
I'll just fix that later. So, So, this
requires discipline and requires backing
by management in order to
to keep things going to to keep this
practice alive especially in the
beginning. Um
And the problem is I mean I
you've probably been in in this as well.
There's this sort of thing I like to
call integration hell. Um you've been
working on a project for for couple of
month and have different people several
different small teams working on
different parts. Communication didn't
work too well. And then
a month before the final shipment, you
sort of throw everything over the fence
to the central build and integration and
test team and things won't even compile.
And after 2 weeks you get them to
compile and find out nothing works
together. And this is really hell
because it's very very difficult to fix.
This is the exponential thing you
mentioned in the beginning. Um If
Um different parts of the system don't
initially or often times they don't
initially fit together exactly.
And if you find that out after 1 hour or
after 10 minutes or whatever, it's very
easy to fix because you still know what
the problem might be. You find if you
find out after a week, it's hard to fix
because you there are so many subtle
dependencies that were added. It's It's
to find out which part causes the
problems and after a month or so it's
basically impossible to really fix and
it's a huge effort that needs to go in
there. So the idea is to
keep the different parts together
to avoid to not to to to avoid giving
them them the chance to go in different
directions.
And this is really really important to
do even and if your system is so big
that you can't do it really continuously
do it at least every night.
And if you didn't do that so far you
might want to start by doing it once a
week but the
what with the goal of getting to once
every night.
This is also goes back to other
practices um
small working in small increments um
because um
if yeah you want to to split your
changes into small things that can be
integrated and then tested in the
integration.
Exactly and if you remember back our
first XP episode
you see the the value behind is
feedback. I I mean
it's you can take all the practices we
discuss right now and map them back to
the values. I I guess maybe it's it's
getting more yeah understandable the the
value discussion from the first episode
if you just try to map the practices and
the values sometimes.
So let's jump to the last primary
practice incremental incremental design.
Um which is
This is one of the most controversial
practices of all.
Okay what's the idea? The idea is to
postpone any design decision
to
at the latest responsible point of in
time.
You don't do a big design up front in
your project. You you do it
as
late as possible actually so
just when you get in your new new story,
your new user story,
and it does need a change in
architecture
and design, do it when you need it, not
front up. Just when you know, yes, I
need it right now, not anything in
advance.
I like to illustrate that with a little
story, which is about Kent. I mean, this
this practice and how to interpret it
was controversial between among the
different XP people, but
I read somewhere that Kent Beck said
that even for for business systems
he would not start by
saying, "When Okay, when we start the
system, we know that we will need a
relational database."
But
even such fundamental architectural
decisions until you really found out
that you did need a relational database,
which would obviously be quite
quite early usually, but still he would
not um
start with this assumption, but have
even such fundamental assumptions be
driven by the actual development
process, by feedback.
I I guess that gave some discussion.
Yeah, some of the other XP XP people
said they wouldn't go as far as that,
but that's the idea to sort of step back
and leave behind
assumptions that might or might not
apply to this system, because in the
beginning the idea is the beginning you
don't really know much about the system,
and some systems
sound like they that like a relational
database is a good idea, but later you
found out it isn't, and then yeah,
you you might want to take it out.
And the the idea behind this, of course,
is
the experience shows that you do a lot
of things in advance you don't need any
time in the future. So, a lot of people,
architects, developers, project
managers, whatever, everybody has his
part in there um
to to make systems more um future safe,
or how how would you call it? And
actually, um it's much more effort put
into making things in advance that
doesn't get needed anytime in future uh
than it would take to make even hard
changes in architecture when it comes,
because the system is much smaller if
you put out all this uh stuff, and um
just do the things you really really
need. Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, exactly. The idea, or one of the
drivers behind extreme programming, is
to make changes easy, to make changes
cheap.
And you get the best benefit out of this
cheapness if you don't actually don't
spend the effort to design up front. I
mean, you can do that. It doesn't do
much harm usually, or it might even do
harm, but
anyway, even if it doesn't do harm, you
don't have much benefit from it, because
um
making the changes later isn't very
costly. So, the idea is in the
beginning, you don't really know if you
need a relational database or not.
In for for for some systems, uh for some
for most systems that you have a
relational database, I'd say, you know
that up front, and that's okay. I mean,
you don't have to discard all your
experience, but I'll just keep Stay with
this example anyway. Let's say you
There's a system you don't really know
if it needs a relational database. So,
you start out, one way or the other,
without spending much time analyzing all
the requirements that that might come up
later. You just start with a system, and
once you find out that your initial
decision was wrong, that's fine. You
just change it then, because that's
cheaper, and gets the the overall job
done better and faster than if you had
spent the time in the beginning to think
about this. This is the idea behind
extreme programming. Refactoring later.
And actually, there um
I mean, some of you might know the this
um
cost of change curve um that that
uh yeah, will get taught in the the
universities and will is printed in a
lot of books which basically says the
later you do a change or you find
something to change
that the more it will cost and this is
not linear but it's
exponential and the idea of XP is here
to keep this curve as flat as possible
to make change
not costly in in future and
when you have done this and it's it's
done through unit tests through pair
programming through this incremental
design stuff
you can work completely different
in your project and other techniques do
work so one of the the very basic
assumptions is to to change this cost of
change curve actually otherwise it
wouldn't work
Exactly so all these practices play
their part in
I mean the the traditional curve is
exponential
it's like
if changing something during during
analysis costs one unit of money it's 10
units of money during architecture 10
100 unit design and 1000 unit
implementation that sort of thing
and the idea well the claim that
can back makes for extreme programming
that this curve is flat
the cost does not vary it is just as
costly to make the change
during development as it would be during
analysis
Okay so what do you say we just do a
walk through of XP project so let's say
we are approached by someone who says
build me a um
build me a system that
helps me sell things through the
internet
and we are an XP shop or we want to do
things the XP way what do we do
First thing here to mention is
e XP is not just programming team or
process thing. It
even influences the way or it it
massively influences the way you
interact with your customer.
So,
what you don't do
let's take it this way.
You don't get an
and contract or do a contract with a
customer where is exactly written down
what he wants at a fixed time point. So,
you you have to to
explain your customer that you're an XP
shop, that you work with him together to
find or to build the solution actually
that his involvement is important and
that you only can win can can be
successful if you build your software
together. And he has an important part
here. You both do risk sharing here.
It's it's not fixed price contract,
whatever however you call it.
It it feels different for for the
customer and actually even if XP becomes
became
well more common in the last few years,
my
experience is you still have to to
yeah, explain your customer that it's
that way and because he he usually has
no experience doing broker projects. So,
you were saying is XP means it's not a
fixed price project, but actually sort
of
it's an ongoing thing, time and material
payment.
Yeah. And
at some point in time the customer can
say, "Okay, this is enough. I'm not I
don't want you to go on and I just take
what you have now."
Exactly.
So, how
this is quite interesting because often
times customers want to know how cost
how much things cost in advance.
They need to allocate their budgets,
that sort of thing. How do you deal with
that in an extreme programming setting?
Mhm, I don't want to discuss it in in
deep in depth here because it's it's a
actually really complicated thing.
Um, easiest way is to to of course um do
time and material project, but that
doesn't work for every customer.
Um, you you there are actually different
um kind of uh contracts you can do that
that works. Uh you you can um
well, the customer can fix a budget, but
then you have to um
the requirements are not fixed. You have
to leave one of the the
key drivers of the project open to to
make it possible to to reach your goals.
So, um
complicated issue. Um, a lot to read and
on the web on this even contracts on the
contracts how to work this out.
Um
but maybe a bit too much for for you to
discuss this.
So, the idea is um it works best with
time and material, but there are
different models. Um, you can read it up
on the web. And I mean obviously, if
your customer approaches us, we can give
him an estimate of how much it will
cost.
Yeah.
It's just that this is not a binding
estimate because the requirements are
not binding. So, it's sort of like a
trustful relationship. Um, we honest
give give the customer an honest
estimate estimate, and the customer
trusts us that this is an honest
estimate. So, yeah. It's based on trust.
And And when you take this first step,
um which is usually the hardest because
if you don't know your customer, this
trust thing is um hard, of course. Um,
when you're really on the project,
usually the customer very
or gets a feeling that you you have a
trustful relationship because he is on
site with you actually. Uh he has guys
in your team and sees how you work. So,
um this is usually really a startup
problem problem, but it might be a hard
startup problem, actually.
Okay. So, so let's say um
Okay, we estimate it will take 3 months
and cost you um 300,000 um
euros.
So, what happens then? The customer
says, "Oh, great. That's my budget.
That's fine with me. That meets my
deadlines."
So, what what we've done uh here is
actually our quarterly cycle. We have
this um overview planning then this
rough planning. Um what comes next is um
yeah, we really jump very very fast into
our weekly cycles and into our
iterations. So, um
um we sort of get together our team of
four people
and say, "Here's your room. Decorate it
any way you want. Create your own pro-
productive atmosphere and get started."
Getting started means you write your
first user stories. Your team and your
onsite customer and that's maybe we
should go into more depth here
uh right now. Um but your team and your
onsite customer sit together in the in
in the room and work out the first set
of user stories.
so actually at the moment at when the
contract is made between us and our
customer
the other company that gives us the
contract um
there is no fixed set of requirements
that anyone has to agree on. That is
sort of postponed.
We sort of say, "Okay, we've got a rough
idea from one meeting, let's say. And
then um we want to get going and for
that we need user stories. How do we get
those and who is this ominous onsite
customer?"
Okay, let's start with onsite customer.
Um
often discussed point. Um
there are
the basic idea or the the first um
explanations were um
it's okay from your customer
who knows how to or actually works with
the software afterwards. That's
important. It's not
some manager from there who tries to
guess what the software needs. It's
a person who actually has to work with
the software afterwards. So, he he knows
what really is important from business
side, but he also needs the competence
to make decisions. What comes in, what
doesn't come in.
And this is already very
hard to find someone who works with
software, has the competence to decide,
and knows every aspect of the software.
So,
what
Yeah, one of the things that's changed
over the years with with XP
is it doesn't have to be one person. It
It's might be a team
of persons for different aspects, but
and that's still the important part of
it.
He He or the team has to be on site with
you. He is actually
the whole day with your team in in the
the team room and works together with
you. He does test functional tests. He
does user stories. He does
prioritization of user stories,
whatever.
But he is actually there. He's not
someone in a different company who
where you can call him. He has to be on
site
Actually, one one thing is that you have
someone on site in the same room who is
empowered to make binding decisions for
the com for the for your customer.
And who is also an sort of expert who
really knows what the system should feel
like
so that those decisions will actually be
sound and actually be supported and lead
to a working system.
And the third thing what I understood is
um this person or group of persons needs
should be on site, become part of the
team,
which is a huge step of building trust
between you and your customer, building
trust in both directions.
Um so that your your progress will be
visible, your approach to things will be
visible,
and also the um you will and you will
have a benefit or you will have a
benefit of actually um receiving quick
feedback and receiving quick decisions.
So we have this let's say we have one
on-site customer. We have a company
we're working for is ideal. They
actually send us one of the end users.
Um
and this person is on site with our um
four people.
Mhm. Okay. So the first thing they to do
do together is uh write user stories. So
they they get a
some cards, index cards, and um the
on-site customer customer ideally writes
um the the most important uh user
stories down
on the cards. Um he he writes just a
bunch of them uh down on the cards and
um
tries to of course write the most
important uh Of course in XP you as you
have this um
uh
idea of saying or making the
uh it possible for the customer to say
the project is finished now and all the
important stuff is in and the stuff
that's now isn't implemented is not so
important. So you prioritize your uh
user stories by business priority,
whatever that means, by by by value for
your customer.
So the idea of course is that the
on-site customer writes down the most
important stories to him.
So So on day one uh the team gets
together and starts discussing things
and writing down user stories. How how
much time do they spend writing these
stories before they actually dig into
before they boot their computers and
start coding.
Okay, I I guess as we really really
started first iteration here and team
and customer don't know each other, it
it takes longer than usual. Usually
it would take just a few hours. So,
maximum a day.
But, as it's the first time
it might be
a bit longer, of course, because you
have to to get known to each other and
stuff like that. So,
Okay, but it's it's it's So, it's really
really short. It's not spending its time
in upfront analysis. So, the idea is to
get started coding as quickly as
possible.
As I said, a few hours maximum.
So,
of course, this is not
it it sounds a bit simple. It's not that
simple in in
real world that the customer sits down
and writes its story and the developers
sit around him and and watch him
writing. Of course, it's it's a
dialogue. He explains what it doesn't
mean that the developers get an idea
what this story I said that it's just
one or two sentences actually mean to
him what what he really wants when he
says
calculate rate or whatever.
So, it's it's a discussion here
Okay, so let's say after 2 days we have
our first set of
of stories
and these stories are and our answer
customer says, "Okay, this set of
stories is efficient at first. Let's get
started with them. So, what happens
next?"
Okay.
The developer
gives rough estimates how long it takes
to implement a story. So, so
you give them the cards or the customer
gives them the cards and they they try
to figure out to to think about how long
it simply takes to to implement these
stories.
One interesting point here,
of course, for
especially the when you do it the first
time, you think in in days or
real days or whatever. Um,
one thing is
to mention here important thing is
that you may or that your your estimates
are relative.
So,
um, you take your first card and say
your team says it takes whatever, one
day. Let's take
Say it takes one day. So, you then you
take the next card and um
you get a more precise estimate usually
if you not just think about, "Okay, I
think it takes two days." Um, but you
compare the both stories. You you you
estimate relatively. So, you you look at
your second story and say, "Oh, I guess
it takes double the time from our first
story."
So, usually you get a better estimate
this way.
Um
the and
very important, we will see see in the
next iteration why this relative
estimates are important. For the first
iteration, it doesn't make that much
huge difference, of course.
what about what about the basic
infrastructure that needs to be in place
before, I mean
uh the onsite customer probably won't
think about um setting up the um
the servlet engine, let's say it's a
Java project, setting up the servlet
engine and getting all the basic
plumbing in place. That probably won't
be part of any of the stories that needs
to be done before for every single so
this every single story that the
customer or onsite customer wrote down
probably.
Mhm.
Um
again depends on on your your start
position. Usually when you're a project
shop, um, you have a lot in place. I
mean, uh built
environment, all that stuff.
Usually it's it's easy to set up if
you're completely new to business, um,
it might
take some while to to set these things
all these things up because there's a
lot, as you said, test environments and
service engines and whatever.
one one thing is the actual
infrastructure, but then I meant the the
specific code like um
being able to sort of
creating the database table, the object
relational mapping layer, whatever. That
that sort of thing is probably not
visible in any of the user stories and
needs to be done before anything that is
of actual business value can be done.
Yeah, and that's that's a completely
different thing from from these first
time startup stuff because
as said, we have an incremental design
where you you have to change your
architecture and develop your
architecture on the fly all the time.
So,
if you have
um
normal um additional effort for for
building these kind of infrastructure,
servlet engine, integration, whatever,
you you estimate it together with your
story. It might be that there are
very very huge um and huge means as
large as a normal normal user story is
um
things to do. Um
for example, it takes a day to whatever
install a servlet engine and set it up
correctly and integrate it.
the basic infrastructure classes for
customers and for products and um create
the object relational mapping layer
that actually makes them available for
the business logic.
That's
um oh, I I I have a few problems with
this one.
First,
if the the list was too long. I don't
think um it's a good way and maybe it
this is the the link back to the
discussion
up front design from
um
Exactly, that's what I was getting at,
yeah.
So, Uh, I wouldn't really do a complete
infrastructure setup with the first
feature.
Okay, so let's say the let's get let me
concrete. Let's say the user stories are
going something like this. One user
story that is really important is
um
enter a new product with the product
database.
Sort of administration administrative
work. And the other thing is allow
an an end user to view the list of
products with their prices in the
browser. Let's say those are the two
user stories that were prioritized most
highly.
Okay.
Um
I would say for for the first one I
would say
it's if you estimate it you will discuss
all the things you you you mentioned. I
need a solid engine whatever whatever
all the points. And if you put all the
estimates in your user story gets too
large. So you break it usually up. And
if you afterwards have two user user
stories you have to take care
that your user story is still So
basically what you do is
introduce a new user story for your
whatever that database setup for a
Okay, so that So you enter So you create
sort of technical user stories and
explain to the onsite customer that
these technical user stories need need
to be done before any of the original
user stories can be done.
But and that's why it's it's so so hard
actually to explain. First of all
always write it in in customer language
I would call it. Don't say I need an
relational database with an ORM mapper
or whatever because the customer doesn't
know what you mean. He he doesn't see
any value in that. So just always
describe it in in sentences that your
customer actually knows what's the
benefit for him because afterwards he
has to decide if you will do it or not.
So if it's something like I will
introduce hibernate to our um
mapping stuff.
The customer will not choose this user
story anytime. So,
that's not really good. Just describe it
in in the right
you do that for these for these stories?
For these things?
Like getting the infrastructure code
written that you need for getting the
basic a basic architecture in place
that can support the other user stories
that you start with. How would you
phrase that?
Um
And that's the the second important
point I already mentioned for. I
wouldn't do it all in one story. I don't
think it's it's good to to have all
infrastructure in in one story. You have
to
I don't think any feature
that that is small enough to get to as a
user story should be that large because
afterwards you implement all your
architecture front up and just the
business stuff afterwards. Usually you
you can get away and implement some
feature just entering it in a web mask
for example. You don't need the database
right now. Second thing, you make the
the the
thing persistent. So,
split it up into smaller parts that
still give customer value and explain
what the value is. So, introducing your
relational database for example gives
the customer the value that the entered
product whatever is available the second
time he logs in. So,
split it up split it up in in business
perspective
not in technical perspective and
don't do all the infrastructure stuff
front up.
You need some stuff of course I said
build environment and all these things
are different kind of story but
the usual business stuff
Um, you shouldn't implement all this
front up because then you have this big
design up front
and even worse you implemented
Okay, so we have the initial set of user
stories and they were discussed with the
with the development
mem- with the developing members of the
team and there are some stories were
added
with the wording at
of the terminology of the customer.
Yeah.
And then the customer makes the decision
which of these go into the first
iteration.
Exactly.
Based on the estimates.
I said
you split you you maybe even emerge some
user stories if they are too small there
to to that may tracking is makes sense.
So
you have your your final set and
afterwards the customer and only the
customer has the right to decide which
stories go into your iteration and which
not.
Takes the cards and
you have estimates and the first time
you you usually usually get
or start with something like
days or whatever is time efforts.
So you can calculate how many of the the
stories you roughly want to do in this
first iteration and the customer
actually he sorts them by priority.
So you you get away from the I mean I'm
sure you you too have this problem
sometimes that you have 200 priority one
features to implement and non priority
two features. So bring them in the
actual order or the customer has to
bring them in the actual order how to
yeah implement
Okay, so now we have a list of
user stories that should go into our
first iteration of one week.
And then we actually start coding,
getting splitting into pairs and
start coding, writing our tests,
emerging the
continuous build.
And at the end of this week we have
sort of finished, let's say.
Exactly. Um
just just to mention the name, um what
we discussed right now, um the the
splitting of user stories and the
estimation and the priority
prioritization uh is called planning
games in XP terminology. So, um yes, you
do first the planning game, then all the
development with all the practices we
already discussed just first
um the development and uh at the end of
um the
iteration, the one or two-week
iteration, you um should have, and
that's the rule, so um you must have um
running software that fulfills the
stories that you your customer
prioritized.
So, what does the customer do? Of
course, in in these two weeks after
prioritization, uh all the user stories
um
testing. Simply. Um
anytime you you get a feature
implemented, the customer has
first of all, he he does interactive
testing, but also uh if he uses uh some
test frameworks like uh Fit, for
example, he can do with the help of a
developer for maybe um automated
acceptance tests.
So, what do we have? We we have a
complete run in an iteration.
What needs to be done additionally? Um
all the well, after iteration work,
so-called.
You have the release. You have now the
way uh the possibility to calculate the
metrics. You you have a number of
stories um implemented. Let's say we
have four stories implemented. You have
um the estimates, the initial estimates,
and with all these uh information, you
can roughly estimate how much
or how many user stories you will able
to do in the next iteration. The The
idea is called yesterday's weather. You
You just look back and see
I don't know in in 1 week we can do the
work of three estimated days, for
example. So, next week we usually should
be able to do the same amount of works.
That's That's how
metrics or speed is actually team speed
is calculated and used to estimate how
long your project
Yeah, will take.
So, we we now have
a complete run through through an
iteration, how it works. And
what What happens next? Well, next
iteration. So, we start again with the
planning game.
We now have all the information from our
previous iteration. So, we know how much
our How many stories will fit in an
iteration, how the team works together.
The All gets a bit more fluent and it
gets better by time. And
that's also true for for the metric
stuff. The more iterations you have, the
better the speed is actually
Yeah, the the more reliable your your
speed estimates are on this way.
So, we have one iteration and then the
next and then the next and then the
next. Um when is the project actually
finished? I mean, there's always some
new wishes.
Some new user stories.
Exactly.
Um very simple. When the customer says
it's finished. So,
when you you're running out of stories
or important stories or stories not
important enough that the customer wants
you to give money to implement them, um
the the project is finished. And that's
one of the the great things for your
customer actually when you And you have
to sell XP to your customer because it's
a lot more work than usual project. Um,
he gets or he just has to pay exactly
for the things he needs, not more, not
less. So, very great thing actually for
a customer. Yeah.
So, actually the customer can pull the
plug on a project anytime he wants, sort
of
terminate the the the contract at a
week's notice, that sort of thing.
That's at least the the XP perspective
on this thing. I mean, in in in real
life you usually have contracts and
stuff like that. So,
you would handle it a bit different in
most situations. Nevertheless, in theory
and from from XP perspective, yes, that
would be the the way it goes.
So, we talked a lot about how to get
buy-in of a customer for XP.
But, that's only one of the
groups you have to sell XP to. The other
group is the people inside your own
company. So, let's say
Yeah.
one of our listeners wants to get XP
started in their company.
How do they get it? How do they get Do
they get buy-in? How do they get it
started?
Um
Buy-in,
it's a lot of political stuff you have
to to know all the the advantages of XP
and there are a lot. I'm actually a huge
XP fan. So,
I'm really convinced in that XP is one
of the best development processes right
now. So, um
just learn the
advantages of it and learn how to sell
it. How do I start XP? Well, the best
idea in my opinion still is get someone
who really did it before.
Nothing can compare to this. No book
reading, no podcast, nothing comparable.
You need someone who really has done it
before because it actually is hard to
implement even if it sounds very, very
easy, it is hard, believe me. Um
So,
um next thing is if you have someone or
not, I hope you get someone who really
did it before,
um test if you really can deal with
test-driven
development and pair programming because
that's not everybody's thing. I mean,
especially pair programming
um is a hard thing uh and not everybody
likes it and so um
test if your team or your your peers and
you do really
feel or get comfortable with um pair
programming and test-driven development.
Um and then the practical stuff, just
start with the user stories. As simple
as that.
So, if you don't get management buy-in,
you're um one of the things that I
found with experience is it sometimes
actually works to just do it without the
explicit approval of management.
If you're convinced that it actually
saves effort and increases speed and
increases quality, one way to do it is
just implement it. Start doing it
subversively.
Um and then after a week or two when
management notices, you can have your
first result that you can actually show.
Yeah.
Can work, but um on-site customer is
always a problem there. You you need a
customer that that helps you here and um
if your management and your customer um
are the same person or same whatever, um
you might into run into problem here.
But yes, I I would agree uh and a lot of
the XP techniques are all really can be
factored out, but nevertheless, know
what you do. As said, um global code
ownership without unit tests can be uh
Yeah. Unit tests are basically the
foundation for
uh
unit tests and refactoring is basically
the foundation for all the other
practices I think. Yeah. But um
speaking of the problems with the
on-site customer I think we are getting
to the problems that you might run into
problems and limitations and I think um
having an on-site customer is um I mean
certainly it's difficult if your
management does not agree but is
generally a problem I would think to get
someone who's actually an end user to
get them to spend 100% of their time in
your one room together with the software
team and work on this project.
For for most customers I think working
with this would just be not be an
option.
Yeah and and not only he has to be all
the time with your team he has to be
competent um he has to know what to do
and he has to have the rights to decide
what to do so uh that's
uh
I
unfortunately that's that's so seldom I
mean um if you think about it's it's
strange that it's such a huge problem
because usually the customer should have
um
the the
should have the pressure to get a result
from you and should be uh should want to
to get engaged to all the stuff but um
in in practice it's a huge problem. I
would say the the
hugest problem of all.
I agree and I think it's much of the
reason is the culture because for
decades software has been developed in
differently it's with communication
through documents that I think. Yeah.
But I think one thing that actually
works quite well although it is not ex-
XP in the strict sense anymore is to
have some sort of proxy
for the customer on-site.
Um the sort of um
lowest profile approach would be to have
one member of of your local team be the
person to communicate with the customer
spend time on the phone reading writing
email
maybe even reading the specifications
that are there in writing to sort of
build up knowledge and then also be the
person who negotiates on decisions with
the relevant people at the customer
side.
Mhm.
So, this person would then become the a
proxy for the actual customer and take
the role of onsite customer. It's not
quite as good as having the actual
person who makes the decisions onsite,
but it's a workable approach if you just
can't get someone.
Yeah.
And maybe one idea to add here,
um
you can could argue that um
XP makes this thing explicit, but um how
could another development process really
work without something like an
onsite customer? So, uh I I guess it's
really an an an usual problem to any
software project and just because XP
really states that I'm not sure if it's
worse than a different or other pro- um
other process, yeah.
in a way of you're obviously right, but
then other processes address this
problem in different ways. For example,
by having people the forcing people to
actually think about spend time thinking
about the requirements.
And of course, those requirement
documents will never be perfect,
but they will they usually give you a
better understanding of the the actual
um things that need to be done than just
writing user stories up front. So,
Yeah, but
you need time to for this.
time, but it's much easier to get the
specification documents
than to um to get the an onsite
customer.
Those are just two different approaches
to to solving the same problem, and the
onsite customer is the solution that
leads to better software,
and at least that's what I'm convinced
of, but still um
writing the specification documents is
the usual approach that customers are
used to.
Okay, next problem for for my side, um
the all the social aspects, pair
programming, all this stuff. Um I I
often heard um XP just works for senior
developers who are really great
developers because they have to know
everything to do design
blah blah blah. But in my experience
that's not the problem. The problem are
the social aspects actually. The people
have to communicate in a different way,
have to communicate
all the time, have to be have to feel
responsible, have to take responsibility
for for stuff
act proactive to peer decisions all that
stuff. It's It's not technology is not
the problem. Programming is not the
problem actually in my experience. All
the social aspects are really really
difficult and if you have the wrong team
here, you might end up in a disaster.
Yeah, I agree.
One one variety of this
things that are one of one of these
reasons that is often given against XP
against
pair programming that's the thing is
I mean in XP every person works on every
single part of the technology. So every
person works on the database code if
there's a database. Every person works
on the graphical user interface code.
Every person works with XML.
And whatever. So
I heard people say that this means
everyone needs to be an expert on these
things which is also really not true.
I mean obviously you need to have at
least one person
on the team that knows these
technologies you're going to use
otherwise you're in trouble anyway. You
need to give people time to learn it
whatever.
So let's assume you have at least one
person for each of these things. Then
the usual approach would be if someone
wants to do some work on the database
to just get this person who knows the
database and pair up with this person.
So actually it is works very well if
people are not senior developers.
Because it helps to spread the limited
knowledge throughout the team to help
people to learn from one another.
Even if I mean, it's always difficult to
develop to develop software if you don't
have any senior developers. If you don't
have no one with experience, you're in
trouble anyway. But even but even then
XP would help because um
there are two people thinking about the
same design decision at the same time.
If one person feels unsure about this,
they would discuss it and so you would
have a team that is comfortable with the
design you're you're having. So the
whole team is comfortable with the whole
design, knows the whole design, that
sort of thing, and refactors things. So
even in such a situation with no single
senior developer, you're in less Let's
see, you're not out of trouble, but
you're in less trouble than you'd be
with other approaches.
Yeah, absolutely.
So
um anything else to
Yeah, well, there's one prejudice
against extreme programming that I would
like to to talk about. Um maybe to wrap
up the episode. Um and that is that
extreme programming Well, actually, this
is often said about Agile development as
a whole,
that extreme programming is just
hacking. Extreme programming is just
like "Oh, we don't want to to spend time
writing documents, doing testing, all
these things we don't like. Let's just
um get to the keyboard. Let's dig into
the code and do some hacking." And this
is really prejudice that has given Agile
development quite a bad name.
And I think this is a huge
misconception. And it's very important
to address this at at the management
level if you want to do Agile
development because if a project goes
wrong,
um
I've heard managers sort of sort of
joking about saying "Oh, we're doing it
Agile now."
Meaning we're we've left behind all sort
of organized process. No one knows
what's going on. And this is just We
don't do anything. We just left all the
documentation and the planning and and
the testing and anything. And this is a
huge misconception. Actually, extreme
programming is the single most
disciplined process that I know.
Um it requires
very much It's a very very It's very
strict. I mean,
the
um if you do extreme programming,
there's no line of code that goes into
the system that was not reviewed by a
second programmer.
Um in extreme programming, no code gets
written unless there's a user story for
this code and the customer prioritized
it saying, "This goes in."
If you do extreme programming, means
that you do um you do no write no code
or well, basically no code
that is not tested by a unit test that
is run
continually by all the developers.
There's many times every day. So, it's
very very disciplined.
Um
Not only that, uh extreme programming
also says
just on a on a minute basis what to do,
when to switch keyboards. While pair
programming, it's it's really really
tough. I mean, um most other um methods
uh just say, "Do your coding."
Right.
And not anything more.
Well, they they say and write these
2,000 documents afterwards.
Yeah.
Exactly. So, it's it's really detailed
and really it it needs discipline very
much.
Right. This brings me to one thing I'd
like to add, and that is a prejudice
that in um extreme programming and agile
development, there's no documentation.
Actually, this is nonsense because the
customer can say can write a user story
at any point in time saying, "I want
documentation." And then, of course, you
write documentation. So, it it just
makes it explicit um that this takes
effort, and the customer decides how
much documentation the customer wants.
Just as an aside, um I think this is one
of the other prejudices.
But getting back to this um thing about
hacking and programming, actually um
extreme programming is very disciplined.
And
but but this prejudice shows how
important it is to actually do it
wholeheartedly.
If you just say
um well, I'll do the planning game, but
pair programming and refactoring and
unit testing are not for me, you'll be
in loads of trouble.
And especially unit testing. We're
getting back to this again and again and
again. Unit testing is the fundamental
the the most fundamental practice. And
well, it goes together with refactoring
usually. So, refactoring and unit
testing are the single most fundamental
practice on which everything else
builds. If you don't have that, nothing
will work.
So,
um actually actually Oh, yeah. But
And there's one true part to to this
prejudice. I actually I think extreme
programming is much more
code-centric than most other development
processes. It's much more focused on the
the actual stuff that gets to the
customer. The the real
Yeah, code actually. So,
it is much more coding-centric,
hacking-centric if you want, than other
processes, but that doesn't mean it's
not disciplined.
Exactly. Um it's Yeah, it it
takes some switching of the priorities
of the approach to programming in the
developers. I mean, one thing is giving
up code ownership, sharing
responsibility for every line of code.
Another thing is to
learn to read and write unit tests,
which brings us to the episode on unit
testing we're going to do, which is
really really important. But this is is
different approach um
to if you want to understand code, to
not expect there to be
lots of documentation documents that you
can read. I mean, those It's okay if
they're there, but they're often
outdated anyway. So,
but the um it's a skill that actually
needs to be learned. It takes It doesn't
take very much practice, but it takes
some practice
to read good unit tests in order to
understand what code is about.
It also means that the you need to clean
up the design
continuously
for the code to be understandable from
the code itself, from the unit tests, to
have good names. All these refactorings
are important. If you leave them out,
the code won't be understandable and
you're in trouble.
But if you have
um good unit tests and good names and
good structure overall, then
not not very difficult to extract the
architecture even and the design from
the code itself, especially if there is
a team that and the the whole team knows
about the design decisions and the
tradeoffs involved and everyone is
familiar with different parts of the
system.
So these things
work only if you take the whole bunch of
them, if you actually do
unit tests, if you do refactoring, if
you clean up things, and if you avoid
code ownership.
And because you share responsibility and
knowledge of the code with all
developers, and if but if you do these,
then actually XP isn't far from hacking,
it's quite the opposite. Actually, it
means that everyone
takes responsibility for every change
and people work together. And there is
good documentation in the form of
knowledge that is spread and you good
unit tests and good design.
Okay.
So, as we are already have one of our
longest episodes, I guess we should end
here.
Um
anything else to add?
Give XP a try and give Agile development
a try, but especially XP.
Start with unit testing refactoring and
if you're familiar with that, go to pair
programming and add the other practices.
Give it a try. It's a great experience
and it really brings a team together. Um
if you get the chance do it.
Yes, I hope we didn't
keep you away with our too long episodes
here. It's not as hard as it sounds
here.
Definitely not. Yeah, well, I think this
is about wraps it up.
Thanks for listening and yeah, hear you
next time.
Thanks for listening to Software
Engineering Radio. If you want to get
more information about Software
Engineering Radio or if you want to give
us feedback, please go to our website at
SE-Radio.net.
You can also contact the team at
team@se-radio.net. Although we prefer
entries in our comment system on the
website so other people can see what you
think. Software Engineering Radio wants
to thank Henning
Pauli for the intro and outro music as
well as Lipps and for providing the
bandwidth.
This episode of SE-Radio as well as all
other episodes is licensed under
Creative Commons license. See the
Software Engineering Radio website for
details.